Your Highness,
殿下
the peach blossom pastry and preserved fruits
您为谢娘子订的蜜花桃酥
you ordered for Lady Xie have arrived.
和几味蜜饯送来了
Please have a taste
请您试吃
and see which one
看一看哪一种
agrees with Lady Xie best.
最合谢娘子的口味
Who made this?
这是谁做的
Lift up your head.
抬起头来
It's you?
是你
Your Highness still remembers me.
殿下还记得奴婢
Take the others away.
把其他人带下去
Everyone, leave the room.
都退下去吧
How do you know how to make hawthorn cake?
你怎么会做山楂糕
Before entering the palace,
奴婢在宫外时
I had a long stay at Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
于靖安王府长住过一段时日
I often heard the servants talk about
常听府里的下人们谈起
Lady Xie making hawthorn cake for Your Highness.
谢娘子为您做山楂糕
So I tried my hand at making some using her method.
便学着她的手艺做了些
Did anyone allow you to do that?
谁允许你做的
Now, I get mad at the sight of hawthorn cake,
孤现在看到山楂糕
for it always reminds me
一想到心爱的夭夭
of who my beloved Yaoyao is with.
和谁在一起就来气
Get out!
滚
Yes.
诺
Mother, it hurts.
阿母 疼
Do be gentle, Mother.
轻点吧 阿母
Drop the act.
还装
It does hurt a little.
还是有点疼的嘛
You used to dream of traveling far and wide
以前你总想着游历山川
and exploring the world.
行走天下
After what just happened,
走过了这一遭
do you still want to do that?
以后还想去吗
Mother,
阿母
only when I left Jiankang
夭夭走出剑慷
did I realize what the real world is like.
才知真正的天下为何物
There aren't fine clothes and lavish feasts,
没有锦衣玉食
nor thousands of dazzling lights.
也没有华彩千灯
Take the girl in court today as an example.
就像今日大堂上那个女孩
Just like that, she saw her own brother
她就那么亲眼看着自己的哥哥
die a tragic death right before her.
惨死在自己面前
Perhaps she already
可能她这辈子
lost her only family.
再也没有亲人了
To add to that...
而且
nobody will ever fix a honey drink for her anymore.
也没有人再给她煮蜜水喝了
By contrast, some people are utterly vile,
可是有的人心又是那么地坏
just like Cui Jun.
就像那个崔浚
He even harmed his own little sister
他为了雀骨令
just for the Phoenix Heart Tokens.
连自己的亲妹妹都不放过
Right.
对
Empress Wenxi and I were as close as sisters.
我与文熹皇后情同姐妹
She often talked about her older brother
常听她聊起哥哥
to me, describing him as an upstanding
说她兄长是个胸怀大义
and ambitious man.
志向高远之人
To survey the mineral deposits of Ye,
为了勘察大邺矿藏
he travelled to nearly every part of the country.
几乎走遍了全国
But based on what Cui Jun did today,
可今日见崔浚所作所为
he is completely different from what Empress Wenxi said.
跟文熹皇后说的完全是两个人
I've never seen this.
从未见过
Then, has there been
那你父亲
anything odd about your father after he returned
自漠北游历回来之后
from the northern desert region?
可有何异常
I once heard from my mother
我曾听母亲提过
that my father was severely injured
父亲从漠北回来时
upon his return.
身受重伤
After he recovered,
伤愈过后
he became completely different.
便像换了一个人一样
He was cold, indifferent,
性情冷漠
violent, and harsh,
暴戾严苛
unlike the loving parent he used to be.
再也不复往日的慈爱
Shortly after that, my mother passed away.
没过多久我母亲便离世了
Please think again.
你再想想
Any other change?
还有吗
My mother also told me
母亲还与我说过
that my father somehow
不知为何
became interested in studying
父亲喜欢研究上了
mineral deposits and maps.
矿藏和舆图
Please think again.
你再想想
What does your father
你父亲平日里
enjoy eating?
都喜欢吃什么
He doesn't like or dislike
没什么喜欢的
anything in particular.
也没什么不喜欢的
However, in recent years,
但是这几年
I've noticed that my father no longer enjoys tea.
我发现父亲不大爱喝茶了
Instead, he prefers milk
反而爱喝牛乳
and all sorts of pastries made with milk.
和牛乳做的各种糕点
This wheel?
轮盘
Why does he have this?
他怎么会有这个
Isn't it what I made for Shao Yang
这不是当年在北秦
years ago in Northern Qin?
我做给少秧的吗
You disappeared for 20 years.
你消失了二十年
I really thought
我还真的以为
you were dead,
你已经死了
Chu Zhu.
楚竹
Nothing gets past you.
还是没能逃过你的眼睛啊
You put on a disguise mask
你换了一副面孔
and began hiding in Southern Ye.
隐藏在南邺
Shao Yang instructed you to do so, right?
是少秧让你这么做的吧
This is my master's order
这是主人的命令
and my mission.
也是我的使命
Then what about the real Cui Jun?
那真正的崔浚呢
Twenty years ago, when he travelled the northern desert region,
二十年前他游历漠北时
I killed him in an attempt to seize the map of mineral deposits
为了夺他绘制的矿藏舆图
drawn by him.
我杀了他
Unfortunately, I was one step too late.
只可惜晚了半步
He had already sent the map back to the Capital.
他已将舆图送回上京
This map was later
而这舆图
stashed in the Phoenix Heart Tokens
后来被文熹皇后
by Empress Wenxi.
藏在了雀骨令中
Let me ask you. Did you also orchestrate
我问你 安陆二氏
the wrongful cases involving the An and Lu families
还有我族人的冤案
and causing my clansmen's deaths?
也是你一手炮制的
I am a slave bought by Shao Yang.
我是少秧买来的奴隶
She is my master.
她是我的主人
Whatever she asks me to do,
她要我做什么
I will absolutely do it
只要我还活着
as long as I'm still breathing,
就一定要去做
including eliminating the An and Lu families and your clansmen,
包括她要我除掉安陆二氏
as she commanded.
和你的族人
Well, well.
好
Not only did my love betrayed me,
不仅我的恋人背叛我
but my best friend also stabbed me in the back.
就连我最好的朋友也背叛我
Not long ago in Jiankang,
前不久在剑慷
I met Shao Yang.
我见到过少秧
How is my master doing?
主人还好吗
Your master
你的主人
got seriously ill.
身染重疾
She passed away shortly after returning to Northern Qin.
回到北秦不久就去世了
Will you continue to work for her?
你还要为她卖命吗
This is a design of mine
这是我设计的
for sealing the imperial mausoleum
用来建造皇陵
with water.
注水封盖
Tell me.
你告诉我
What exactly are you trying to do?
你到底想干什么
To destroy Lingfeng Fort.
毁掉凌风堡
All the iron-contaminated water in the mine
矿洞中被污染的铁水
is sealed under this wheel.
都被封在这轮盘之下
Six hours ago,
三个时辰前
I already activated the wheel.
我已经开启轮盘
Lingfeng Fort will soon be submerged by the polluted water.
很快铁水即将淹没凌风堡
Everyone will die.
所有的人都会死
You're crazy.
疯子
The wheel mechanism is full of hidden weapons.
轮盘机关布满暗器
Mulian Ying,
穆连婴
you will definitely not
你这一去
make it back alive.
必死无疑
All of you will have to die with me!
你们全都给我陪葬吧
My mother just made some honey water.
这是我阿母刚熬好的蜜水
I brought a bowl of it for you.
也给你带了一碗
Drink it when it's warm.
快趁热喝了吧
You didn't poison it, did you?
该不会给我下毒了吧
Yes, I did.
下了
I added in stuff like datura,
什么曼陀罗啊
aconite, and Qianji poison.
乌头啊 牵机药
Why did you still drink it when I told you it was poisoned?
我都说了下毒了 你还喝
Because I wanted to be killed by you.
想被你毒死呀
Is it sweet?
甜吗
Thank you for saving those girls.
谢谢你救了那些女孩
If they decide to hush them for good,
杀人灭口的话
what will happen to these girls?
这些女孩子怎么办
-Please help us!
求求你们救救我们
-Help us!
救救我们 救救我们 救救我们
-I beg you! -Please!
求求你们 求求你们
-Please help us!
求求你们救救我们吧
Also, thank you for saving my mother.
也谢谢你救了我阿母
Does your wound still hurt?
你身上的伤还疼吗
It's normal to get injured in battle.
行军打仗受点伤很正常
This wound is barely anything.
这点伤算不了什么
My hunch tells me something's wrong.
我总觉得哪里不太对劲
Is it about Cui Jun?
可是因为崔浚
When my mother was in Shangjing years ago,
我阿母她当年在上京
she heard from Empress Wenxi
听文熹皇后说
that the latter's brother was originally a righteous man.
她哥哥本是个胸怀大义之人
But now this man has become completely different.
如今却变得面目全非
You don't think
你是不是觉得
he'll easily surrender, right?
他不会这般轻易束手就擒
My own design can't stump me, can it?
我设计的还能难住我
Shao Yang, here I come.
少秧 我来了
Your Highness, the mine collapsed.
世子 矿洞发生坍塌
Yuan Xiaoliu is dead.
元小六 死了
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
Yuan Xiaoliu.
元小六
Master.
师父
Wake up.
醒醒
Yuan Xiaoliu.
元小六
Master!
师父
How exactly did this happen?
这到底是怎么回事
It was my father's doing.
是我阿父
He tried to drag everyone to hell with him.
要与我们大家同归于尽
All the polluted groundwater
被污染的地下水
was kept beneath this mine.
全都被封在这矿山之下
My father activated the mechanism
我阿父开启了机关
so as to drown the entire Lingfeng Fort with filthy water
要让污水淹没整个凌风堡
and take everyone's life.
我们大家都会死
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
You cannot kill him.
你不能杀他
We must bring him back to Jiankang.
我们必须把他带回剑慷
That's the only way to expose the Cui family's crimes to the world
这样才能把崔氏之罪告知天下
and truly avenge those who died a wrongful death!
才能真正为那些枉死的人报仇
This is how justice works!
这才是天理公道
Your master sacrificed his life to save all of ours.
你师父舍命救了我们所有人
Princess Yunzhao,
郡主
truth to be told,
实不相瞒
I'm here at the Grand Tutor's request.
此番我也是受太傅所托
He knew you were likely in Lingfeng Fort,
太傅知道郡主可能在凌风堡
so he asked me to bring you a message.
便托我给郡主带句话
That is, The Xie family in Jiankang
剑慷谢氏
will always await your safe return.
永远待郡主平安归去
No need. All ties between him and me are severed
不必 既然和离
now that we are divorced.
再无牵挂
You are such a free spirit.
郡主洒脱
How admirable.
乐君佩服
After the disastrous happening,
经此一劫
I finally realized
乐君也才知道
that the Phoenix Heart Tokens
原来这世间
truly exist in the world.
当真存在雀骨令
There has always been a saying among people in recent years—
这几年坊间一直传闻
"When the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world."
雀骨出 天下定
I wonder if you...
不知郡主
If the world could be changed
若几枚令牌
by just a few tokens,
就能改天换地
why would Young Lord Xiao bother to implement reforms?
萧世子又何必要改制
The Phoenix Heart Tokens
这雀骨令
are simply something that Empress Wenxi
不过是文熹皇后
left behind for those around her to remember her by.
带给身边人的一些念想
As for that rumored Crown Prince Wenxi,
至于那什么文熹太子
it's pure nonsense.
更是无稽之谈
That day in court,
那日我在堂上
I made a lie out of it
就是为了逼崔浚自乱阵脚
just to cause Cui Jun to panic.
所以才这么骗他
As a holder of a Phoenix Heart Token,
你也是雀骨令的持令人
you were also entrusted with Ye's moving to the south
都肩负着大邺南渡
and the task of aiding Crown Prince Wenxi.
辅佐文熹太子
Crown Prince Wenxi died a long time ago.
文熹太子早死了
He didn't die!
他没有死
Empress Wenxi and I were as close as sisters.
我与文熹皇后情同姐妹
If her son had really survived,
若她的孩子真遗存世间
I would love him dearly.
我该有多么疼爱他
How would I have never shown any care
又怎么会这么多年
for him during these years?
对他不闻不问呢
Good then.
那就好
I was just worried about my brother.
我方才还在为我哥哥担心
If Crown Prince Wenxi truly existed,
若世间真有文熹太子
what would become of my brother?
那我哥哥到时又该如何自处啊
Hearing what you said today,
今日听郡主这番话
I'm finally relieved.
我终于安心了
I shall
那乐君
take my leave then.
就先告退了
How did it go? Did you intercept the letter?
怎么样 截获了吗
Did Princess Yunzhao mention the whereabouts of Crown Prince Wenxi?
郡主是否提及文熹太子的下落
Bring the nanny in Prince Qi's Mansion back to Jiankang.
把岐王府的乳母带回剑慷
Your brother
你哥哥
is not of royal blood at all.
根本不是大邺血脉呢
Yunzhao has long suspected Prince Qi's origin.
云昭早就怀疑岐王的身世
The purpose of her trip to Guazhou
她此番去鸹州
is probably to use the Phoenix Heart Token she holds
恐怕是要用自己手上的雀骨令
to command the other token holders
去号令其他持令之人
to assist the Li lineage of the royal house in gaining the throne.
重新扶持李邺宗室
This is bad. She plans to reveal Mao's real identity.
不好 她要揭发哥哥身份
This is the map of Ye.
这是我大邺舆图
Close your eyes.
你闭上双眼
Throw a dart.
射出飞镖
We will go wherever it lands.
射到哪儿 咱们就去哪儿
No need to shut my eyes.
我不用蒙眼
I'll just throw the dart.
我直接射就行
There's a place called the Cloud Pavilion on Lai Lake.
莱湖有一处水上云间
Let's go to Lake Lai then.
那咱们就去莱湖
You don't like it?
不喜欢
How about we will travel all the way south
那咱们就一路南下
in quest of the best copper mine in the world?
去寻天下最好的铜矿
Mother,
阿母
actually, I...
我其实
Never mind. It's nothing.
算了 没事
So you don't like traveling with me.
你不喜欢与阿母一起游历
Where would you like to go then, Yaoyao?
那夭夭 你想去哪儿
Oh, right.
对了
I just recalled another wonderful place,
我还想到有一处好地方
where you can find your favorite dish, tofu steamed in lotus leaves.
那里有你最喜欢吃的荷叶豆腐
In midsummer, you can take a boat out to sea.
盛夏之时还能乘船出海
How about we venture off to the sea
阿母带你一起去看海
and watch the sunrise together?
看海上日出 可好
Mother, are you writing a letter to Father?
阿母是在给阿父写信吗
Yes.
对
Some things,
有些事
I think, are better explained clearly
我想应该与你阿父
to your father.
说清楚些
There is a problem with Cui Jun's identity.
崔浚的身份有问题
So is with the wrongful convictions of the An and Lu families
当年安陆二氏的冤案
years ago, I'm afraid.
恐怕也有问题
So you're not going back to Jiankang, Mother?
那阿母不打算回剑慷了
No. What about you?
你呢
Are you planning
难不成
to go to the Northern Border with Xiao Wuyi?
你想随萧无衣去北境
Mother, I'm not...
阿母 我没有
I made a promise to my master.
这个只是答应我师父的
I must not break my word.
我不能食言
Yaoyao,
夭夭
what do you think of Xiao Wuyi?
你觉得萧无衣如何
Did you have a good time living
在靖安王府的日子
in Prince Jing'an's Mansion?
过得可都好
Mother.
阿母
I think...
我觉得
he's somewhat different from what people say about him.
他好像跟传闻中的不太一样
He's actually a great general.
是一个很好的将军
"Who says we stand alone?
岂曰无衣
We share weal and woe."
与子同袍
Indeed, he chose
他的确给自己
a rather good name for himself.
取了个很好的名字
But I was asking your opinion about him as a person.
不过我问的是他这个人
He...
他
could be quite annoying sometimes.
有时候挺招人讨厌的
But, I guess, maybe he can be
但大概 可能
considered a gentleman.
算是个君子吧
Let bygones be bygones.
过去的就当都过去了
Young Lord Xiao has agreed to let you go.
萧世子既愿意放你离去
Have you made any plans
你可曾为自己的将来
for your future?
做过什么打算
I'll travel the world with you for sure, Mother.
我当然是去跟阿母游历天下呀
Haven't you already planned it all out?
阿母不是都计划好了
In the past, I was so immature
从前是夭夭不懂事
that I often made you angry.
总惹阿母生气
From now on, I will stick with you all the time.
以后我就日日黏着阿母
We shall never be apart.
咱们永远不分开
How about that?
好吗
You're leaving so soon?
这么快就要走了
What happened at Lingfeng Fort will be known.
凌风堡的事瞒不住
I'm afraid the Phoenix Heart Tokens
这一路怕是有不少人
will be coveted by many along the way.
对雀骨令动心起念
If I travel with you,
我与你们若一道走的话
there might be danger.
怕是会有危险
So I'll take a different route back to Jiankang.
我安排另一路回剑慷
Will you...
你
go back to my mansion
回剑慷
in Jiankang?
靖安王府
My mother and I will send Lejun back to Jiankang first,
我和阿母先送乐君回剑慷
and then head directly south to Shu County.
然后直接南下去蜀郡
Shu County?
蜀郡
Yes. My mother
我阿母说
told me she once saw crystal-clear pools there,
她曾经在那里见过清池
so I'd like to go and see for myself.
所以我也想要去看看
Then...
那你
Try not to get kidnapped.
别让人掳走了
Don't worry.
你放心吧
I'll continue the studies
我师父的火蒺藜
on my master's caltrop fireball.
我会继续研究的
If anything comes up,
等有了消息
I'll inform you immediately.
第一时间告诉你
Good.
好
Well then...
那
I'll get going.
我先走了
Sure.
好
Li!
老李
Here you come.
来了
The usual, half salty and half sweet?
还是老样子 咸甜各半
Yes.
是是
Wait a moment.
稍等啊
My wife
我夫人呢
loves the rice cake you make.
就好你做的饵饼
After being away for days,
她离家多日
I bet she misses this delicacy.
怕是想极了这口
How very lucky of your wife to have you,
您家夫人有您这般上心
such a caring man, as her husband.
真是前世修来的福气啊
Alright. Thanks.
好 多谢啊
Goodbye.
好
Master.
家主
A secret letter has arrived.
送来了密信
I've found out the mysterious Phoenix Heart Token is related to a mine.
我已获知雀骨令之谜与矿藏有关
Besides,
另
Princess Yunzhao and Cui Jun
云昭郡主与崔浚手中
each hold a Phoenix Heart Token.
各持一枚雀骨令
The relationship between Xie Jiayu
谢嘉鱼与萧无衣
and Xiao Wuyi has changed.
已非昨日
Princess Yunzhao will possibly join forces with Xiao Wuyi.
郡主恐与萧无衣联手
I'm ready to go all out.
我欲放手一搏
Why would she partner with Xiao Wuyi?
她怎么会与萧无衣联手
T-That's impossible.
这 这不可能啊
Do not act rashly.
切勿轻举妄动
We'll devise a plan when you're back to Jiankang.
一切回剑慷再做打算
Have this letter delivered to Princess Pingning.
此信派人交给平宁县主
Remember: make it quick.
记住 要快
Yes.
诺
Your Highness, Lady Xie,
郡主 谢娘子
Young Lord Xiao ordered Qing Long and me to escort you two.
世子命我和青龙护送二位
How thoughtful of him.
世子有心了
Let's go, Mother.
走吧 阿母
Anything wrong?
怎么了
Mother, I'm feeling a bit unwell.
阿母 我有点不舒服
Yaoyao, after the incident you just went through,
夭夭 你刚经历这场风波
I'm sure you need to lie down and rest.
想必还需卧躺休息
Why not ride with me instead, Princess Yunzhao?
郡主不如与我同乘
It's a good idea.
也好
I'm fine, Mother.
我没事 阿母
I have recovered.
我都好了
Maybe we should still...
要不咱们还是一起吧
Yaoyao,
夭夭
please listen to Princess Yunzhao.
你还是听郡主的吧
If you get ill,
你的身体若是不好
everyone will be very worried.
大家都会很担心
Be a good girl.
听话
Get some rest.
好好休息
My Lady,
女郎
His Highness said
世子说了
you must not tire yourself out.
不让你过度劳累了
Who on earth do you work for, me or him?
你到底是我的人还是他的人
As long as it's for Your Ladyship's own good,
反正要是为了女郎好的话
I'll listen to it.
我都听
I don't think Your Ladyship is rushing to draft the caltrop fireball
我觉得女郎这么急着画火蒺藜
entirely for Master Yuan.
并不全是为了元师傅
The horse got startled!
马惊了
Oh no!
不好
Mother, Lejun!
阿母 乐君
Mother!
阿母
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
萧无衣 你放开我
Let go of me!
你放开我
Mother...
阿母
Your Highness!
郡主
-Princess Pingning! -Princess Yunzhao!
县主 郡主
-Mother!
郡主 阿母
Princess Pingning!
县主
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主
-Princess Yunzhao! -Princess Pingning!
郡主 县主 县主
Mother...
阿母
Princess Pingning!
县主
-Princess Pingning! -Princess Yunzhao!
县主 郡主
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主 郡主
-Mother! -Princess Pingning!
阿母 县主
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主
Mother...
阿母
Princess Pingning!
县主
-Princess Yunzhao! -Mother...
郡主 阿母
-Princess Pingning! -Mother!
县主 阿母
Princess Yunzhao!
郡主
I found Her Highness!
找到了
Mother...
阿母
The daughter I want
我想要的女儿
is not some puppet who only knows how to obey me,
并不是一个只会听我话的木偶
but a young woman
而是一个
who truly knows what she wants
真的知道自己想要什么
and what she ought to do.
知道自己该做什么的女郎
Your parents are not the ones you can truly depend on—
你真正能依靠的不是父母
only you are.
而是你自己
Mother!
阿母
Your Highness, the coachman is dead.
世子 车夫已死
What about Princess Pingning?
平宁县主呢
Not found yet.
尚未发现
Go on with the search.
继续找
Make sure you find her,
生要见人
dead or alive.
死要见尸
Yes.
诺
Mother...
阿母
My Lady.
女郎
these are Her Highness's belongings.
这些是郡主的遗物
Is anything missing?
是少了什么东西吗
The Phoenix Heart Token...
雀骨令
Could it have dropped somewhere when Her Highness
是不是郡主摔下去的时候
fell off the cliff?
掉出来了
That's impossible.
不可能
I saw Mother place it right next to her skin.
我亲眼看见阿母贴身放置
Is Your Ladyship suspecting that someone murdered Her Highness
女郎是怀疑有人为了夺令
in order to obtain the token?
故意残害郡主性命
Before she fell off the cliff,
坠崖之前
that horse was clearly out of control.
那匹马显然不受控
Mother!
阿母
Go examine the forage
去查一下粮草
and the dead coachman.
还有那个死去的马夫
Got it.
好
We found Princess Pingning!
找到县主了
We found Her Highness!
找到了
Where did you find her?
何处找到的
Your Highness was fortunately
县主命大
caught on a dead branch right by the cliff.
被挂在悬崖边上的枯树枝上
Injured though,
虽然受了伤
Her Highness's life is not in danger.
但是无性命之忧
That's good.
那就好
I investigated many a matter.
南星查了许多事
This is roughly how the incident happened.
大致情况便是如此
The horse went wild
那匹马发狂
because it ate the grains and forage
是因为吃了被污水
contaminated by the dirty water.
污染的稻谷粮草
And all those grains and forage
而那些稻谷粮草
were already sealed by my order.
已经全部被我下令统一封存
I even specifically prepared a horse carriage.
我还特意准备了马车
Now the biggest suspect of Princess Yunzhao's murder
如今谋害郡主最大的嫌疑人
is me.
是我
It does appear so.
明面上是这样
But Lady Xie is very perceptive.
但谢娘子如此通透
The clearer the evidence against Your Highness,
证据越是明显
the less likely Her Ladyship is to suspect you.
应当越不会怀疑世子
Whether she suspects me or not doesn't matter.
怀不怀疑我都不重要
The point is, the deceased is Jiayu's mother.
可她是嘉鱼的阿母
Now, the more care I show,
如今
the messier the situation will be.
关心则乱
My Lady!
女郎
Are you alright, My Lady?
你怎么了 女郎
Jiayu.
嘉鱼
She's burning up.
这么烫
Quick, go get Ruisheng!
快 去叫蕊生
Xiao Wuyi.
萧无衣
Before my mother's fall,
我阿母出事前
had you seen her
你有没有见过她
or heard her mention
或者有没有听她提起什么人
anyone trying to harm her?
想要害她
Does sitting in that chair
坐上那把椅子
mean all the constraints will go away?
就能够不受掣肘了吗
The military is controlled by noble families.
世家掌兵
Whoever takes that post is bound to be
不论是谁坐到那个位置
subject to constraints.
都必受掣肘
That's why I established Beifu,
所以我才会建立北府
an army that doesn't answer to noble families.
建立一支不属于世家的军队
No.
没有
Father...
阿父
Mother...
阿母
♪ One glance from near stirs my heart ♪
萧无衣
I'm here.
我在
Xie Jiayu,
谢嘉鱼
do you know who you are asking for?
你可知道你在喊谁
Jiayu
嘉鱼
Don't be afraid.
别怕
Get some sleep.
睡吧
Dawn will eventually arrive.
总有天亮的时候
Not all the toxins from the polluted water were cleared from Jiayu's system.
嘉鱼矿水的毒尚未解清
Neither did she have time to rest properly.
也没来得及好好休养
Then, Princess Yunzhao's death hit her hard.
又有郡主之事刺激
She turned like this due to emotional blows.
急火攻心才会如此
The remaining toxins in her must be purged.
要继续清除余毒
What medicinal materials are needed?
需要什么药材
I'll have Qing Long go buy them.
我让青龙去买
I have all the common kinds,
普通的我都有
but a rare one is lacking—
但缺一味稀有的
bear gall.
熊胆
My Lady, you're awake.
女郎 你醒了
How long was I asleep?
我睡了有多久了
Two days.
有两日了
What is this?
这什么
It smells terrible.
这么腥 这么臭
It's bear gall, a cure for toxins.
这是解毒的熊胆
Where did it come from?
哪儿来的熊胆
Probably provided by Madam Ruisheng.
大概是蕊夫人的吧
That treasure box of hers surely has
她那个百宝箱里
all sorts of medicinal materials, right?
什么药没有啊
The journey has been paused for too long.
耽误太久了
It's time we headed back to Jiankang.
我们该回剑慷了
My Lady,
女郎
Princess Yunzhao passed away so suddenly.
郡主走得如此突然
How should we hold a funeral for Her Highness?
这丧礼该如何办呢
Theorectically,
按理说
since Her Highness already divorced the Grand Tutor,
太傅与郡主已经和离
her coffin should be placed in the Princess's Mansion.
郡主应该去郡主府停灵
However, the princess's fief,
可郡主封地
namely Yun County, was conquered by Northern Qin long ago.
云郡早已沦落北秦之手
Her control over it was just nominal.
食邑只是遥封
Neither was her mansion
剑慷也从未重建过
ever relocated to Jiankang.
云昭郡主府
Then where should we bring her coffin?
那我们该去何处停灵呢
To Prince Jing'an's Mansion?
靖安王府吗
From now on, I'll stick with you all the time.
日后夭夭就每天都黏着你
We shall never be apart.
永远不分开
Your Highness!
世子
Prince Qi and the Grand Tutor have come.
是岐王和太傅
Yaoyao, where is Lejun?
夭夭 乐君呢
In the carriage behind.
乐君在后面的马车里
She fell off the cliff with my mother,
她与阿母一起坠下山崖
and is still in a coma with severe injuries.
现在还重伤未醒
Bring her back to the palace now,
快送回宫
and summon royal physicians!
宣太医
How did Princess Pingning
怎么会是平宁县主
and Yunzhao fall off the cliff together?
和云昭一起掉下山的
Father,
阿父
it was all my fault.
是我的错
I was supposed to share a carriage with Lejun,
原本是我与乐君一起同乘
but I felt unwell
但是因我身子不适
and needed to lie down,
需要卧躺
so we swapped carriages.
这才换了马车
Because the horse was startled,
是因为马匹受惊
her carriage plunged off the cliff.
车子摔下山崖去了
Father,
阿父
I...
我
Grand Tutor,
太傅
Jiayu didn't wish for
郡主之死
Princess Yunzhao's death,
非嘉鱼所愿
nor does she have anything to do with it.
亦与她无关
How does it have nothing to do with her?
如何与她无关
Who told you to switch carriages with Yunzhao?
谁让你跟云昭换马车的
If it had never happened,
如果没换
it would've been you who died.
死的就是你
It couldn't have been Yunzhao, right?
怎么会是云昭
Everyone of the Xie family, listen!
谢氏上下人等听令
Princess Yunzhao and I simply adopted Xie Jiayu.
谢嘉鱼不过一介养女
She was not given birth by us.
并非我与郡主亲生
From now on,
从今往后
this woman is no longer the daughter of the Xie family.
谢氏不认此女
She is not allowed
不许此女
to step into the Xie Mansion ever again.
再踏入谢府半步
Guards!
来人
Yes.
在
Escort the princess's coffin
把郡主的棺椁
back home.
请回家
Yes.
诺
On the genealogical record,
宗牒族谱上
I, Xie Huaigui, and Yunzhao,
云昭此生
will remain as husband and wife forever.
都是我谢怀归的妻子
We were never divorced.
不曾和离
I'm taking my wife home.
我接妻子回家
None of you can stop me.
看你们谁敢拦我
Grand Tutor!
太傅
Xiao Wuyi, go back without me.
萧无衣 你先回去吧
I need a word
我有些话
with Mao.
要和阿茂说
I didn't expect you to be involved in the Cui Family Case.
真没想到你会卷入崔氏案中
I was frightened upon receiving
乐君给我来信的时候
that letter from Lejun.
我都吓坏了
Don't beat yourself up.
你千万别自责
What happened to Lejun and Princess Yunzhao was an accident.
乐君和郡主的事是场意外
It wasn't your fault.
不是你的错
My mother didn't die of an accident.
我阿母并非意外而死
What?
什么
Her Phoenix Heart Token has gone missing.
她的雀骨令不见了
Someone must have
是有人
murdered her for the token,
为了夺她的雀骨令而害了她
and Lejun became collateral damage.
也连累了乐君
Do the Phoenix Heart Tokens truly exist?
当真有雀骨令
Cui Jun and my mother each had one.
崔浚和我阿母手中各有一枚
If it hadn't been for these tokens,
当初若非为此令
I wouldn't have been tricked into going to Lingfeng Fort by Cui Jun.
我也不会被崔浚骗去凌风堡
He originally intended to use me
崔浚本想用我
to force my mother to hand over her token.
来逼我阿母交出雀骨令
Yet he failed in the end.
但最后功亏一篑
I find Xiao Wuyi suspicious.
我怀疑萧无衣
The horse went wild
马匹发狂
for eating the grains in Lingfeng Fort,
是因为吃了凌风堡里
which were polluted by the dirty mine water.
被矿水污染过的稻谷
All those grains
而这稻谷
had been collected and sealed by Xiao Wuyi.
已被萧无衣清剿封存
No one could access them except him.
除了他 没有人再有
He already coveted the Cui family's mines
他早就在凌风堡时
back in Lingfeng Fort.
觊觎过崔氏矿产
So he's the biggest suspect.
所以他嫌疑最大
Lejun is severely injured and in a coma now.
乐君如今重伤未醒
When she comes to, please
她若是醒来后
ask her to do me a favor and think carefully
你让她帮我仔细想一想
if there is any other witness or clue.
还有没有什么人证线索
I've someone to find the coachman's family
我让人去找了马夫的家人
in the hope of gaining new clues.
希望能有什么新线索
But, Yaoyao,
可是夭夭
if you're truly suspecting Wuyi,
你若真怀疑无衣的话
then you must not return to his mansion.
便不可回靖安王府了
If not, how am I supposed to find
若是不回靖安王府
my mother's Phoenix Heart Token?
怎么才能找到雀骨令
This item is of great importance.
此令极其重要
He must have hidden it somewhere secret.
一定被他藏在某个隐秘的地方
Perhaps he has it on him.
或许就在他身上
As long as I find this token,
只要找到雀骨令
I'll be able to prove him to be the murderer.
我就可以证明他就是凶手
Yaoyao...
夭夭
Mao.
阿茂
My mother is dead.
我阿母死了
The only person who loved me unconditionally
这世上唯一偏爱我之人
in this world died a wrongful death.
死得这样不明不白
I swear to find out the murderer,
我一定要找到害死她的凶手
whoever that may be.
无论是谁
I will make sure justice is served for her.
我一定为她讨个公道
Maybe Your Highness
世子
should have the bear-induced wounds checked by the physicians.
熊爪伤还是请太医来看一下吧
Have Cui Jun and Cui Shao'an
崔浚与崔少安
been properly arranged?
安排得如何了
Yes, all is done as per Your Highness's orders.
按世子吩咐的 都安排好了
What happened at Lingfeng Fort will soon be known.
凌风堡的事瞒不住
With two Phoenix Heart Tokens appearing at once,
一下子出来两枚雀骨令
anyone would be tempted.
是个人都会蠢蠢欲动
I'd like to see
那倒要看看
who will show up for them.
究竟谁会跳出来
Xiao Wuyi, I'm back.
萧无衣 我回来了
You finished that talk with Yizhi?
和易之都说完了
Yes, I was giving him some advice about Lejun.
有些乐君的事情嘱托他一下
Are you explaining to me?
你在同我解释
I'd like to have a clean room.
我想要一间干净的屋子
Wensheng Courtyard has always been yours.
闻笙苑一直都是你的
I want to set up a memorial tablet.
我想要立牌位
Before my mother died,
我阿母生前
she had decided to divorce that man.
已经决定和他和离
I'm afraid her spirit in heaven
我怕她英灵在上
would hate to return to the Grand Tutor's Mansion.
不愿意回太傅府
So, I plan to set up a memorial tablet
所以我想在闻笙苑
for her in Wensheng Yard.
给她立牌位
This way, I can mourn for her.
好替她守丧
As I said,
我说了
Wensheng Yard has always been yours.
闻笙苑一直都是你的
Feel free to make your own decision.
你自己决定就好
Got it.
好
Lejun,
乐君
the imperial physician said
御医说
you hit your head when you fell off the cliff.
你摔下悬崖的时候撞到了头
That's why you've been in a coma.
所以你一直睡着不醒
Are you going to stay asleep like this
难道你要一直这样
and never wake up again?
睡着就再也不醒过来了吗
What exactly happened
在那马车里
in the carriage?
究竟发生了什么
Yaoyao said
夭夭说
Xiao Wuyi murdered Princess Yunzhao to get her Phoenix Heart Token.
萧无衣为夺雀骨令害了郡主
She has also sent people
夭夭也派人
to find the coachman's family.
找到了这马夫的家人
Though the latter is dead,
马夫虽已死
his family might have seen
但马夫的家人
who replaced the forage
有可能看到谁把粮草
with the polluted grains.
换成了稻谷
As long as the witnesses arrive in Jiankang,
只要证人一回剑慷
they can immediately testify
就可以立即指证
who exactly harmed you and Princess Yunzhao.
究竟是谁害了你和郡主
Li Lejun, you're actually conscious, aren't you?
李乐君 你是醒着对吧
Are you sure you want to keep up the act?
还要再装吗
Mao.
阿兄
Are you alright?
没事吧
Have Yaoyao and her people really found
夭夭他们真的找到了
the coachman's family?
马夫的家人
Did they truly see who tempered with the forage?
他们真的看到了
No...
不
It can't be possible.
不可能
So it really was you.
果真是你
Please punish me, Mao.
请阿兄降罪
Why on earth did you do it?
究竟为何
This matter has nothing to do with you.
此事与阿兄无关
It's better for you not to know the truth.
阿兄还是不要知道的好
You caused Princess Yunzhao's death,
你害了郡主
and framed Xiao Wuyi for it.
还栽赃给了萧无衣
Xiao Wuyi is not someone to be trifled with.
萧无衣可不是这么好对付的
Tell the truth already.
你再不说
If not, what are you going to do
到时候他查起来
when he starts investigating it?
你该怎么办
Speak up.
说
Prior your trip to Guazhou,
你去鸹州之前
what exactly did you plot with the Grand Tutor?
究竟和太傅密谋了什么
Why did you murder Princess Yunzhao?
为什么要害郡主
Because she had a Phoenix Heart Token.
因为郡主手里有一块雀骨令
Because Crown Prince Wenxi is still alive.
因为文熹太子还活着
And more importantly,
更因为
Princess Yunzhao knew that you, my brother, are
郡主她知道哥哥你
the Grand Tutor's son.
是太傅之子
What?
什么